Why do wombats make cubic poops? At
first we thought it was because they
stack so well. Without the round sides,
they won't roll away. That makes it a
lot easier to mark your territory. But,
there are plenty of other scent marking
animals that poop, but none of them make
it quite so angular. So, then
researchers thought maybe it had to do
with the shape of their digestive tract.
But again, no. No square sphincter, no
square guts. Instead, scientists now
think it's to do with them living in
super dry parts of Australia. To deal
with the extremely hostile conditions,
they have to get as much water as they
can from their [music] food. And to do
that, their guts have a special set of
alternating muscles, which pinch and
pull their guts much like this rubber
band. You can see if I grab either end
and pinch and pull, [music] it forms
this square shape. So, the squareness is
a byproduct of this gut pinching.